<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Parbhat Puri</title><link href="http://www.parbhatpuri.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.parbhatpuri.com/feeds/javascript.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.parbhatpuri.com/</id><updated>2015-01-30T18:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>AngularJS Superhero of Single-Page Application (SPA)</title><link href="http://www.parbhatpuri.com/angularjs-superhero-of-single-page-application.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-30T18:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Parbhat Puri</name></author><id>tag:www.parbhatpuri.com,2015-01-30:angularjs-superhero-of-single-page-application.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;AngularJS is the Superheroic JavaScript MVW Framework for enhancing HTML for Web Apps.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt="Angular-JS-logo" src="https://angularjs.org/img/AngularJS-large.png" /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's Web Apps are not that Simple, they should offer more-native-app-like experience to the user. The Web Application should not reload the whole page whenever a user request something. First we have to familiar ourself with the concept of Single page application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single-page application (SPA), is a web application that fits on a single web page with the goal of providing a 
more fluid user experience similar to a desktop application. In a SPA, either all necessary code – HTML, 
JavaScript, and CSS – is retrieved with a single page load, or the appropriate resources are dynamically loaded 
with technologies like AJAX and added to the page as necessary, usually in response to user actions. The page does 
not reload at any point in the process, nor does control transfer to another page. Interaction with the single 
page application often involves dynamic communication with the web server behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Now, how angularJS fits itself into Single Page Application concept.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AngularJS also known as angular is an Open Source Web Application Framework maintained by &lt;strong&gt;Google&lt;/strong&gt;. It helps in
creating rich Internet Applications which are easy to maintain and test. Angular works by first reading the HTML
page, which has embedded into it additional custom tag attributes. Those attributes are interpreted as 
directives telling Angular to bind input or output parts of the page to a model that is represented by standard 
JavaScript variables. The values of those JavaScript variables can be manually set within the code, or retrieved
from static or dynamic JSON resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTML was not designed for dynamic views, but it is great for declaring static documents. Angular helps to extend
HTML and gives behaviour to HTML which helps in declaring dynamic views in web-applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my Future posts I will discuss the features of angular like directives, Controllers, Models, Routes, Factories, services etc. The following picture helps to understand the power of angular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt="Angular-JS" src="http://i.imgur.com/U87M5vo.png" /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Javascript"></category><category term="angularjs"></category><category term="2015"></category><category term="Programming"></category></entry></feed>